[music]
>> Welcome to this 2026 release wave two
version of Business Central launch
edition. This video is about some new
things we added to data analysis. So, in
this session we're going to talk about
analysis mode, list of views, and
profiles.
In analysis mode, two new features. The
first is that you can now use system or
fields in your analysis tabs or views.
And the second, which is something that
is not in the major release, but coming
in a minor
uh ability to bookmark an analysis tab.
So,
we have added these what's called
so-called system fields, created by,
created on, modified by, modified on.
Um I think hm I actually quite a few
years ago.
They exist on all tables in Business
Central, but until now they were not
kind of visible um into analysis mode,
but but we have remedied that.
So, no matter if these fields are shown
on the list page, they will also be
always be available
in uh the columns menu in analysis mode.
So, in this example I have taken the
sales orders list
and added uh modified by and modified
at.
That could for instance be a quick we
wait to see which salesperson was the
last one touching a sales order. So,
that's a very easy way to to do that in
analysis mode, even if those fields are
not shown on the sales order list.
Here's another example on the customer
list where I did created by or modified
by. So, that could be some history um
here not on the sales order, but on the
customer, but the same thing applies.
Now, coming in version 29.x,
hopefully here in the one of the first
minor versions, is ability to bookmark
an analysis tab or analysis view. Here I
have again the sales order list with an
analysis view.
And if I open that menu here, we you can
see that there's a new option called
bookmark view.
When I do that, then well, the view is
bookmarked.
We did this because a lots of both list
views and analysis views are for a lot
of users considered mini reports. And
and therefore it it it's would be nice
to be able to navigate directly from the
role center.
Speaking of list views, since we did
bookmarking for analysis views, we
thought, why shouldn't we do the same
for a normal list view or these saved
filters?
So,
here in the sales order list now, just
in a normal list page mode,
um I've taken the open sales order
view,
if I can find my mouse here,
and if clicking on the ellipsis, there's
also a bookmark view action.
And what happens when you have done
that, well, then you get your
list view bookmarked to the role center.
Now, profiles is a way to share
artifacts for all users that share the
same profile.
And here you can now use the system
audit fields to add them to pages. And
also, you can bookmark the bookmarking I
just showed for analysis views and for
list views, uh those can be added to a
role center for a profile. So, if you
modify pages for profiles, um let's have
a look here. I have opened the page
designer, navigated to adding fields,
and if I search here for system, you can
see that the system fields are
available, created at, created by, and
so on. So, on the sales order card,
I can simply add modified by with either
the username or with a full name. So,
that's also something we add in the
analysis mode versions.
And that would for this particular
profile be a way to see
that type of auditing information on the
card. And for all profiles, users
sharing that profile, they would see
this extension to the page.
Um, and of course, you can you can in
profiles add bookmarks. So, so as part
of this, you can also bookmark analysis
tabs or list views to a profile.
And that's it. Just one more thing. If
you want to learn more about
uh data analysis, or sometimes we also
call it ad hoc analysis, the those types
of things where you don't have a report,
um the landing page is as always
aka.ms/bc-analytics,
and then scroll down to ad hoc data
analysis, and here you find everything
for analysis mode, for list views, and
for the new features that we have here
in in version 29.
That's it for now. I hope you have a
great launch edition, and hope you have
other great videos you want to see. I'm
done here, so have a great day. Bye.